Today's דף daf is מ"ז Mem Zayin and we pick up where
very bottom of מ"ו עמוד ב'. Mem Vav Amud Bet. We pick
up where it says
let's try let's pick up where it says כהיכא Koheicha 1 2
3 6 lines from the bottom. It actually says כהיכא Koheicha on
two repeating lines, we'll start from the higher
one כהיכא. Koheicha. All right, anyway.
Here we go. All right, sorry about that. Okay, so כהיכא. Koheicha.
So it says like this, it says
sorry, we'll get it working. All right, so the issue at stake
was that we've been dealing a lot with the position of Rabbi
Shimon. And for a large major part of the discussion was the
issue about what narrow areas of מוקצה muktza does Rabbi Shimon hold
of and do we rule like Rabbi Shimon? The last discussion we
had in here had been when we ended yesterday was that the
one thing that does seem clear is that one of the problems
that Rabbi Shimon has with the lamp when it's burning, which is
the one of the few cases of מוקצה muktza he holds by,
is that you presumably it's you can't move it while it's burning
because you might come to extinguish it. But why is that a
problem? I mean so what if you do it? It won't definitely
happen. It's unintentional. It's דבר שאינו מתכוין. davar she'eino mitkaven. That should
be permissible according to Rabbi Shimon. So why not go ahead and
move it while it's burning?
And the first answer of the גמרא Gemara is look, when Rabbi
Shimon normally allows something that you're not intending, that's when we're not
dealing with a דאורייתא, d'oraisa, with a biblical מלאכה. melacha. Here it's
a דאורייתא. d'oraisa. Here if you were to extinguish it intentionally, it
would be a דאורייתא d'oraisa of מכבה. mechabeh. The case of dragging
the bench, the classic case of Rabbi Shimon, even if you intentionally
drag the bench in order to make a ditch, that would only
be a דרבנן d'rabbanan because that's a שינוי, shinui, that's an unusual
way of making a ditch by dragging a bench. Okay? So that's
why so we're going to reject this in a minute because as
you know we generally rule אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven is always permissible
whether you're dealing with a דאורייתא d'oraisa or דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Okay? That's
a huge part of our שבת Shabbos is that we if it
won't definitely happen it's okay even if it's a דאורייתא. d'oraisa. But
that's what we're trying to suggest is the difference and that's why
he would not want you to move the lamp. So let's take
a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. It says like this:
כהיכא דכי מכוין איכא איסור דאורייתא, Koheicha d'ki mechaven ikka issur d'oraisa,
again we're five lines from the bottom, כי לא מכוין גזר רבי
שמעון מדרבנן. ki lo mechaven gazar Rabbi Shimon mi'd'rabbanan.
When if you were to do it intentionally it would be an
איסור דאורייתא, issur d'oraisa, like extinguishing the lamp, at least under some
circumstances that would be דאורייתא d'oraisa if you're trying to make charcoal.
Then even if you're unintentional that's when Rabbi Shimon would not allow
it. כהיכא דכי מכוין איכא איסור דרבנן, Koheicha d'ki mechaven ikka issur
d'rabbanan,
but in case where even were you to intend it would only
be rabbinic like dragging the bench, which is a שינוי, shinui, כי
לא מכוין שרי רבי שמעון לכתחילה. ki lo mechaven sharei Rabbi Shimon
l'chatchila.
That's when Rabbi Shimon allows you to do it לכתחילה l'chatchila if
you're not intending and that's why he wouldn't let you use the
lamp. So the גמרא Gemara quickly rejects that. מתיבי רבא, Masive Rava,
Rava asked on this: מוכרי כסות מוכרין כדרכן ובלבד שלא יתכוין בחמה
מפני החמה ובגשמים מפני הגשמים. Mochrei ksus mochrin k'darkan u'vilvad shelo yiskaven
bachama p'nei hachama u'v'geshamim p'nei hageshamim.
That here we have Rabbi Shimon's position of allowing אינו מתכוין eino
mitkaven even by non-שבת Shabbos areas. Because it's always an interesting question
when things are not transgressions on Shabbat, one of the reasons might
be it might be a special aspect of Shabbat. שבת Shabbos you're
only חייב chayav for מלאכת מחשבת, melaches machshevet, intentional act. Intentional well
I shouldn't say very specific type of intention. Like for example the
whole concept of מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufa, doing
the act but for its non-intended purpose is an exemption. I mean
think about let's say you did that by another עבירה. averah. You
know, okay like I was I don't know, you know I was
over on the איסור issur of cutting off my you know shaving
my beard with a razor but I didn't do it for the
intended purpose. I mean who cares, you did the איסור, issur, right?
But by שבת Shabbos the idea of כוונה kavana plays an important
role in defining the prohibited act. So when Rabbi Shimon says that
אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven is allowed, the question is is this specific
to שבת Shabbos where כוונה kavana is so sacrosanct or even in
general? And this גמרא Gemara as well as many other גמרות Gemaras
make it clear that Rabbi Shimon's position applies in other areas as
well that אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven is allowed and one of the
classic cases it brings is the case of שעטנז. shatnez. And here's
what it says, this is the משנה. Mishnah. מוכרי כסות מוכרין כדרכן
ובלבד שלא יתכוין בחמה מפני החמה ובגשמים מפני הגשמים. Mochrei ksus mochrin
k'darkan u'vilvad shelo yiskaven bachama p'nei hachama u'v'geshamim p'nei hageshamim.
People who sell their garments can wear the garment on their, you
know, wear the garment they're selling on themselves if that's an easier
way to transport them. Even if some of those garments are שעטנז.
shatnez. However, they cannot intend, I mean hopefully they're selling's not you.
However, they cannot intend for in the summer for it to protect
them from this from the sun and in the rainy season to
protect them from the rain, meaning they can't wear them with the
intention of how you wear a garment to protect to protect yourself.
You can wear it as a form of carrying it and that's
not the prohibition. והצנועין, Vehatznuin, but those that are, you know, meticulous.
משפילין במקלו אחריהם. mashpilin bemaklo achoreihem. They don't wear it on their
back; they actually put it on a stick and carry the stick
behind them and like have a traveling rack because they don't want
to wear it even with not intending incorrectly, so not having the
intent that would be a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says, and
it assumes that that's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon because it כוונה kavanah
plays a central role and it makes it permissible. So it says
הכא דכי מכוון איכא איסורא דאורייתא איכא. hacha dechi mechaven ika issura
de'oraissa ika. Here by שעתנז, shatnez,
if you're intending to wear it as clothing, you'd be transgressing the
דאורייתא de'oraissa of שעתנז. shatnez. כי לא מכוון, ki lo mechaven, but
when you're not intending to do it for that purpose, שרי רבי
שמעון לכתחילה. shari Rabbi Shimon l'chatchila. רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, assuming it's
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, who else is lenient by intention? There רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon would allow it, so you see even when it
comes to a biblical issue and this is so central as I
said for our observance of שבת Shabbat that we allow אינו מתכוין,
eino miskaven, not intending if it won't definitely result even by דאורייתא.
de'oraissa. So you see רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows it even by
דאורייתא. de'oraissa. So please explain to me, says the גמרא, Gemara, why
you cannot move the lamp while it is burning. Now you might
want to say one minute though, didn't we say according to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon that a day or two ago that when it's
burning there's an idea of הוקצה למצותו, huktza l'mitzvaso, set aside for
the מצוה, mitzvah, so the same way as you can't take סכך
s'chach off of a סוכה? sukkah? So yes, but remember that is
not your classic מוקצה; muktza; that's not even limited to שבת, Shabbat,
you know that could apply even like on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed.
You know, you can't you know take the סכך s'chach off of
your סוכה. sukkah. So and there the prohibition is you can't do
something with the object that removes it from serving you know from
sort of serving its מצוה mitzvah function. So as תוספות Tosafot points
out, you can move a lamp all the way around your house
and it can help you serve the מצוה mitzvah function; it's with
you wherever you need it. The only thing that would, so that's
not a problem of הוקצה למצותו. huktza l'mitzvaso. The only problem of
הוקצה למצותו huktza l'mitzvaso is taking the oil away from the lamp,
right? So you got the lamp here and the oil somewhere else,
that is removing it from its מצוה mitzvah function. And of course
you can't do that anyway because it's מכבה, mechabeh, so the one
application would be where it has dripped, already dripped on a plate.
And there, that's why you can't like benefit from it; that's seen
as the nature of הוקצה למצותו huktza l'mitzvaso for the issue of
the lamp. Not moving it, which is not a problem, but you
know consuming it, that is specifically the nature of the problem; that's
why the משנה Mishnah says אין נהנין ממנו, ein nehenin mimenu, you
can't benefit from it. But the גמרא Gemara now says, oh, that's
all very nice, but it sounds like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't
even allow you to move the lamp. Why should that be? It's
not for the prohibition of extinguishing, that's אינו מתכוין. eino miskaven.
So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. אלא אמר רבא,
ela amar Rava, so rather רבא Rava said top of מ"ז עמוד
א', mem zayin amud aleph, הנך לנר שמן ופתילה. hanach l'ner shemen
u'ftila. You know,
forget about the case, meaning leave them alone: the the flame, the
oil and the wick. Those are special things; even for רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon that's a type of מוקצה, muktza, a real מוקצה muktza
that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree to. Why? הואיל ונעשה, ho'il
v'na'aseh, excuse me, not נר, ner, excuse me, excuse me I jumped
that.
The the lamp, the oil and the wick, those things are מוקצה.
muktza. You cannot move the lamp, the oil and the wick, why?
הואיל ונעשה בסיס לדבר האסור, ho'il v'na'aseh basis l'davar ha'asur,
because they are a base, a support for the forbidden thing. While
we've mentioned the lamp, the oil and the wick, they're all a
base for what? What's the only thing we didn't mention? I mentioned
it before accidentally: the flame itself. So you take a look at
רש"י: Rashi: לדבר האסור ולשלהבת l'davar ha'asur u'leshalheves ובהכי מוקצה מודה רבי
שמעון דכלי טפל לשלהבת בעודה בו. uvehai muktza modeh Rabbi Shimon shekeli
tafel l'shalheves be'oda bo.
Okay, so this as I said to you way when we began
this whole, we've been digging מוקצה muktza for about a week now
all on this one משנה Mishnah about the oil and the lamp,
that what is the nature of this מוקצה muktza of the burning
lamp? So sometimes that's described, I mean the גמרא Gemara described it
initially as מוקצה מחמת איסור. muktza machmat issur. So what does מחמת
איסור machmat issur mean? So initially רש"י Rashi said you can't move
it because you know you're because it would make it go out,
and since you couldn't move it בין השמשות bein hashmashot because of
the איסור issur that it would lead to כיבוי, kibbuy, it would
lead to extinguishing, therefore it's off limits the whole time even after
it extinguishes. That's all very nice, but that's not רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. First of all, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says I don't go
by when שבת Shabbat begins, you know I reassess everything at the
moment. But number two is even moving it when it's burning, as
the גמרא's Gemara just asked, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon there's no איסור
issur to move it. In theory, if it weren't for מוקצה muktza
you could move a lamp around according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
אינו מתכוין eino miskaven because you're not intending, אינו מתכוין eino miskaven
it won't definitely happen. So that's why the גמרא Gemara says it
cannot be this issue of מוקצה מחמת איסור, muktza machmat issur, that
means off limits because you might extinguish it. So what does it
mean? It's a different מוקצה: muktza: בסיס לדבר האסור. basis l'davar ha'asur.
There's this idea that the flame itself is מוקצה. muktza. I mean
I don't know how you move a flame itself, but the flame
itself is completely off limits and therefore the whole rest of it,
the wick and the and the oil and the lamp, are all
a support for that flame. That seems to be a type of
a sui generis category, like the only type of thing we have
that you know the thing itself is מוקצה muktza because somehow I
don't know it's doing an איסור, issur, it's burning, it's whatever. You
know that that we never hear like any other thing that falls
into the same category of this idea of the flame, the burning
flame's itself what is מוקצה, muktza, right? But anyway, because normally רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't hold of it, but somehow the flame itself
is מוקצה. muktza. itself more than, it's not just, you know, more
than the rest of the lamp, that is primarily what is מוקצה.
muktzah. Everything else is supporting it. That is a case that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon would admit to. Now תוספות Tosafot points out, let
me look in תוספות, Tosafot, we had to mention all three things:
the lamp, the oil, and the wick. Because if any one of
them, if either the wick or the oil were not considered a
בסיס, basis, why don't you say that like the, what do you
call it? That the wick is a בסיס basis and the שמן
shemen is not a בסיס, basis, or the wick and the שמן
shemen are the בסיס basis but the lamp is not, right? You
know, because the only, if they're like all stacked, so why don't
you only say the thing immediately closer is a בסיס? basis? Because
תוספות Tosafot says if you only say the wick is a בסיס,
basis, then you could move the lamp, because the lamp would be
supporting the problematic wick and the non-problematic oil. And something that's a
בסיס basis to two things,
right, one of them is not problematic, then you could move it.
So you basically have to say that like all of these things
are problematic. Now that is an interesting question in the laws of
בסיס. basis. Right, if you do have something that's basically stacked, right,
you know, does a בסיס basis make a בסיס? basis? Okay, so
if I've got my, you know, let's say it would happen in
a common case where about moving the tray that the candlesticks are
on and the candles are burning. The candles were the בסיס basis
to the candlestick and then, you know, and that's the
בסיס basis and the tray is the בסיס basis to the sticks
and the table. So how much does a בסיס basis make a
בסיס? basis? Anyway, that's addressed in תוספות Tosafot and you look at
תוספות הני לנר שמן ופתילה. Tosafot Hanei L'ner Shemen U'f'tila. תוספות Tosafot
says איצטריך למימר בשמן דנעשה בסיס לדבר אסור דאי לאו הכי לא
הוה הנר אסור לטלטל דהוי בסיס לדבר אסור ולדבר המותר ושרי. Itztarich
l'meimar b'shemen d'na'aseh basis l'davar assur de'ee lav hachi lo havah haner
assur l'taltel d'havei basis l'davar assur u'l'davar hamuttar v'shari.
So you have to consider the שמן shemen to also be a
בסיס, basis, because if you didn't consider it a בסיס, basis, then
the only problem is the wick and then, you know, what's the
problem, then you could go ahead and move it. But now that
the גמרא Gemara does say we consider all three of them a
בסיס, basis, it sounds like we might say that a בסיס basis
to a בסיס basis to a בסיס basis is a בסיס. basis.
So anyway, I will leave that as a, you know, something to
think about, but that is very relevant to the laws of בסיס.
basis. You might have that exact question. In other words, like let's
say this lamp was on a tray that according to רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, you could move the tray.
Right, so maybe not. Maybe there's two ways of reading this.
One is that if it's, the reason here they're all seen as
one unit is because they all come together as a unit, right?
So you know, the lamp with its oil with its wick are
all there to support the flame. So even though they're a little
indirect, they're all primarily there to allow for the flame to burn,
right, as opposed to if you had the lamp on a tray.
So then you could, right, so you could say that in a
normal case you cannot have a בסיס basis for a בסיס. basis.
The point here is that these are all as one unit supporting
the flame.
And since this is a liquid, you know, I understand.
Okay, so that is a good point. I raise that as an
issue for בסיס. basis. Anyway, so that's what we say now. רבי
שמעון's Rabbi Shimon one מוקצה muktzah he holds of is the burning
lamp while it is burning. Why? One reason is הוקצה למצוותו, huktza
l'mitzvato, which means even after it drips away, benefiting from it while
it's burning. And the other issue is that normal מוקצה muktzah moving.
The other issue is very unique to this case, very unique case,
that the flame רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon considers to be מוקצה muktzah
and all these things are בסיס basis to the flame. If you're
not רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and you have broader categories, there could
be other reasons why it is מוקצה. muktzah. For example, the fact
that if you don't hold that you're allowed to move the lamp,
then it could be this מוקצה מחמת איסור muktzah machmat isur that
it was off-limits because you couldn't move it. But רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon who allows you to move the lamp, we have to find
other explanations. Now I do want to say one thing about the
example of שעטנז shaatnez which, about and that that's רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon and אינו מתכוין. eino mitchaven. That's really, although the גמרא Gemara
often quotes it, there really isn't a hard example to understand because
once you say that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees that אינו מתכוין
eino mitchaven and פסיק רישא psik reisha is forbidden, that even if
you're not intending, it's forbidden if it will definitely happen, well that's
certainly the case by the wearing of the שעטנז shaatnez garments. It's
definitely happening that you're getting that benefit of them, even if you're
not intending. Why should it be allowed? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't
allow אינו מתכוין eino mitchaven when it is a פסיק רישא, psik
reisha, when it will definitely happen. So רש"י Rashi often says, well
that's not defined as wearing. The definition of the act of wearing
is putting something on to serve as clothing. When you're putting it
on to carry it or whatever, then you're carrying it on your
back, you're not wearing it. Okay, that's all very nice, but then
it's not relevant to other הלכות halachot about כוונה. kavana. Then it's
very specific to the definition of wearing when it comes to the
issue of כלאים kilayim of שעטנז. shaatnez. So it is interesting that
the גמרא Gemara uses this as an example for רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. It does not seem more globalizable, more abstract, you know, to
apply to other cases because here it definitely is happening. So I
just leave that as well as something to be thinking about. Now
let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. So now we've got the case
of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and about what the issue is with
the lamp while it's burning. אמר רבי חנינא אמר רבי רומנוס. Amar
Rabbi Chanina amar Rabbi Romanos. So said רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina in
the name of רבי רומנוס, Rabbi Romanos, לי התיר רבי לטלטל מחתה
באפרה. Lee hitir Rabbi l'taltel machtah b'afrah.
Now we're moving, effectively if you notice the גמרא Gemara took like
a very elegant the way the גמרא Gemara transitions. It doesn't have
nice transitions. chapter headings, it moves from one topic to another. Like
yesterday it moved from רבי Rabbi, שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* to discussing מוקצה
muktzah, מחמת מיאוס *muktzeh machmat mi'us* which was an aspect of it.
Now it's moving from the רבי Rabbi שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* to discussing
בסיס bassis? *basis*, a base. Okay, and now we're discussing when something
is serving as a base for other things, and it was in
that state before שבת Shabbos? *Shabbat*, that that remains off limits. I
should say the primary importance of, the primary criteria for that is
number one, the thing that was, that was placed on the base,
on the בסיס Bosis? *basis*, was placed there intentionally, and you placed
it there to be there, not like you had forgotten about it
being there. And number two is that it was on there when
שבת Shabbos? *Shabbat* began, and that makes the thing that it's supporting
considered a בסיס Bosis *basis*. So now we're going to talk about
some cases. So רבי Rabbi חנינא *Rabbi Chanina* said in the name
of רבי רומנוס Rabbi Romanus *Rabbi Romanos*, רבי Rabbi *Rebbe* allowed me
לטלטל מחתה באפרה *letaltel machta be'afrah*, to carry a מחתה *machta*, like
an ash shovel, with its ashes. Okay, so אמר Amar, רבי זירא
לרבי אסי *Amar Rabbi Zeira le-Rabbi Assi*, so רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira*
said to רבי אסי *Rabbi Assi*, on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, maybe you
wanted to use the ashes, I don't know, to cover up some
smelly thing. So רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* said to רב אשי Rav
Ashi: *Rav Ashi*, מי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי *Mi amar Rabbi Yochanan
hachi*, could רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* really say this?
Because this was all in the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*.
מי אמר רבי יוחנן *Mi amar Rabbi Yochanan*? והתנן *Ve-hatnan*, we taught
in the משנה mishnah. *Mishnah*, נוטל אדם בנו ואבן בידו *notel adam
beno ve-even beyado*, you can lift up your child even if he's
holding on to a stone, which is מוקצה muktzah. *muktzeh*, או כלכלה
ואבן בתוכה *o kalkala ve-even betocha*, or a basket and the stone
is in it. So so what? Seems like the same idea. You
can move a היתר *hetter* thing with something אסור assur, *assur* in
it. But no, ואמר ve'amar, רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן
*va'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan*, but we said in
the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, בכלכלה מלאה פירות עסקינן *bekalkala
mele'ah perot askinan*, it's only if the basket is filled with fruit,
because then the stone might be different. Like a person doesn't become
a בסיס Bosis. *basis*, okay, but at least the basket could be
a בסיס Bosis *basis*. Why is it can you move it if
it's got a stone in it? Because it's not only a בסיס
basis לדבר האסור *basis ledavar ha'assur*, like we discussed before by the
lamp, it's a בסיס basis? לדבר האסור ולדבר המותר *basis ledavar ha'assur
uledavar hamuttar*, right? It's filled with fruit, it's got fruit and a
rock in it. So that doesn't give it an identity as a
base for a prohibited thing because it's serving as a base for
both a permissible and a prohibited thing.
Yeah, so תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* has some discussion about that, about maybe
I might distinguish between how מוקצה muktzah *muktzeh* is the מוקצה muktzah
*muktzeh*. Stone is very מוקצה muktzah *muktzeh*, so therefore maybe I need
anyway, but right, so there is some issue about that, right, exactly,
there is some discussion about that about what happens if the היתר
*hetter* thing is trivial compared to the אסור *assur* thing. Is that
enough to change the identity of a בסיס basis *basis*? So that
definitely is discussed, right, like again, this whole practice, I don't know
people do it anymore because I don't know if so many people
move their candlesticks off of the table. Most people now light I
think away from the, like near the table, but not on it.
But anyway, it used to be you put like a loaf of
bread on the tray because like food was always considered to be
חשיב *chashuv*. But let's say you left I don't know a handkerchief
on the tray or something like that. So a handkerchief compared to
your silver candlesticks, right, might not be considered חשיב *chashuv* enough. So
there is some question about the relative importance. There definitely is some
question about that.
And over here he says מלאה פירות *mele'ah perot*, so the loaf
of bread would be sufficient.
I understand, like I'm saying, there's even in the הלכה Halacha *Halacha*
there is some question about that. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this, טעמא דאיכא פירות *Ta'ama de'ika perot*, so the reason that
it was allowed was because there were fruit there. It was serving
for both a היתר *hetter* and an אסור *assur* purpose. הא ליכא
פירות לא lo, *Ha leka perot lo*, if there was no fruit
no, the basket would have been a בסיס basis *basis*. So why
isn't the shovel, which the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is assuming that the
ash shovel itself is not מוקצה Muktzah. *muktzeh*. Now why not? I
mentioned the other day and it's very important to keep this in
mind, the difference between כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור *kli she-melachto le-issur* and מוקצה
Muktzah. *muktzeh*. כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור *kli she-melachto le-issur*, which we call מוקצה
Muktzah. *muktzeh*, is actually means it's fundamentally a type of thing that
I don't push away, but normally it's used for a prohibited use,
like a hammer. It's not like if I, if you ask me
do I, would you know, is it possible I could have a
use for my hammer on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*? I say sure, I
can imagine a case I could have a use for my hammer
on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*. It's not like these types of things which
are literally like off limits. And because of that, actually there was
a time where they you'll see later in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
that the prohibition of the כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור *kli she-melachto le-issur* was
a separate גזירה *gezeirah* from the גזירה *gezeirah* of מוקצה Muktzah *muktzeh*.
So there because it's not fully off limits, you're allowed to move
your hammer לצורך דבר המותר *letzorech davar hamuttar* to crack nuts. You're
not allowed to move real מוקצה Muktzah, *muktzeh* לצורך דבר המותר *letzorech
davar hamuttar*, like if you wanted to use this lamp even after
it went down to crack nuts or whatever you wanted to do
with it as a doorstep, you could not. מוקצה Muktzah *muktzeh* is
completely off limits. Because of that, it's important to note that the
idea of בסיס basis *basis* does not apply to a כלי שמלאכתו
לאיסור *kli she-melachto le-issur*, it only applies to real מוקצה Muktzah *muktzeh*.
If I left my hammer on the table, the table is not
a בסיס basis *basis* because the hammer's not really מוקצה muktzah? *muktzeh*,
it's just, I mean again I don't want people to say Rabbi
Bunsen said a hammer wasn't מוקצה muktzah. *muktzeh*, but the point is
it's not the same category. It's כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור *kli she-melachto le-issur*,
it's not intrinsically fully off limits and therefore it does not create
an idea of a בסיס basis, *basis*, that's an important הלכה halacha.
*Halacha* to know. So anyway here the assumption was that this shovel,
this מחתה *machta* for ashes, was something that was a כלי *kli*
let's say שמלאכתו לאיסור *she-melachto le-issur*, maybe, fine, but I want use
it for a היתר purpose, but in it it has real מוקצה,
muktzah. it's got ashes which are like rocks, completely no use. So
how can I move it, why doesn't it become a בסיס? basis
So let's take a look at what the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer. What
what he said is, so he was challenged with this idea, just
says אשתומם כשעה חדא ishtomem keshaha chada quoting a פסוק pasuk from
דניאל Daniel as the גמרא Gemara does this a number of times.
It's like he was like dumbfounded for a second, like he you
know he didn't have an answer. Okay, stumped. But then ואמר, then
he sort of then he came up with an answer and here's
what he said: הכא נמי דאית ביה קרטין. hacha nami de'is bei
kartin. Ah, maybe it's not ashes, it's not only ashes, maybe there's
a little bit, what would you use this for? This would be
an incense burner, not just a shovel like you used to remove
ashes from your fire, it would be an incense burner. So mostly
you have burnt incense in it but there was one or two
little granules of incense left and those are not מוקצה. muktzah, Now
of course what do you mean, you're not allowed to burn them
on שבת? Shabbat Okay, but maybe you can smell them directly, says
רש"י. Rashi. So therefore it was not, it had מוקצה muktzah, and
non-מוקצה muktzah in the incense burner, it had some of those granules
of unburnt incense. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye said:
קרטין בי רבי מי חשיבי? kartin bei rabbi mi chashivi? Since when
does tiny little
granules in for רבי, since when are they significant? They're completely insignificant.
וכי תימא חזו לעניים, vechi teima chazu l'aniyim, oh well you know
fine for him it's not significant but maybe for poor people it
is significant, you know they would appreciate even one little granule. So
for them it would count. והתניא, vehatanya, but we learn in a
ברייתא: braita: בגדי עניים לעניים בגדי עשירים לעשירים. begdei aniyim l'aniyim בגדי
עשירים לעשירים begdei ashirim l'ashirim. That when it comes to the size
of a garment in order to become מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, remember
there's usually two sizes: three by three אצבעות etzba'ot and three by
three טפחים, tfachim, a big difference, okay? So it says that for
עניים aniyim for the poor people even three by three אצבעות etzba'ot
can be significant like they'll use it as a patch or something
like that. But for rich people they throw those things out, they
don't patch their garments anyway, they buy new ones. So for them
it has to be three by three טפחים tfachim which is a
nice little sort of scarf or a real size. So it says
that for a poor person these types of small of clothes, the
בגדי עניים, begdei aniyim, are you know are what are טמא tamei
if it's owned by a poor person. רש"י Rashi says another example
of בגדי עניים begdei aniyim is not just it's a small patch
but maybe it's made by a very coarse fabric, okay. So things
that they would consider to be
significant garments or pieces of cloth for them would become poor and
things that rich people would consider to be significant, nice fabrics and
bigger sizes, you know that would let's say poor they would become
טמא tamei and the things that rich people treat as fabrics would
become טמא tamei for rich people. אבל דעניים לעשירים, aval de'aniyim l'ashirim,
if a rich person owns a little swath of fabric or he
owns some coarse fabric, right, for him he this is heading to
the garbage, he's not planning on using this, right, rich people don't
use these things. So therefore לא, it would not אבל דעניים לעשירים
לא, aval de'aniyim l'ashirim lo, it would not become טמא tamei for
him, it's not a garment. So here too for רבי says the
גמרא, Gemara how can you say this was in רבי'ס Rabbi's house?
ליהטיה רבי. li hitye Rabbi. So how can you say oh it
had ashes and a little bit of you know incense in it?
For רבי the incense was completely trivial. So it's like we discussed
before, you know what happens if on your tray you have your
candlesticks and a handkerchief? Or let's even make a better example: you
have your candlesticks and a napkin. Okay, so at a certain point
it's completely trivial and that does not make it a בסיס לדבר
המוקצה bassis l'davar hamuktzah that has no significance in רבי'ס Rabbi's house.
Sorry, who says this is Rabbi's house?
This is Rabbi Romanus. ליהטיה רבי. li hitye Rabbi. Oh, I guess
it's true, could be רבי allowed me for myself. That's a good
question. Okay, I don't know. It's a good question. Maybe רבי רומנוס
Rabbi Romanus? was one of the members of the household. That's a
good point. Anyway who was רבי רומנוס? I have no idea.
The Steinsaltz say sometimes he gives little biographies.
No, this just doesn't say other than the version that it may
have been מרינוס. Marinus.
מרינוס. Marinus. Okay. All right. Anyway, all right. Anyway,
so moving on, so אלא אמר אביי, ella amar Abaye, so אביי
Abaye says: here's why he let you move out that incense thing
with ashes: מידי דהוה אגרף של רעי. midi dehavei agaraf shel rei.
It's like the sort of the chamber pot, the thing in which
you sort of you know people would basically well yeah diapers for
right whatever but anyway you know when people would go to the
bathroom in it and רעי rei is actually you know you know
defecate. So and therefore that would be very smelly. So even though
that's like you don't have a מוקצה muktzah. more than that in
terms of things that are off limits, but the rabbis let you
move it out of the house, which is interesting questions about taking
your garbage out. Now often your garbage anyway you know we throw
out so much good food you know and so on that it's
not like there's not things in the garbage that in theory are
fit, I mean but we're in the process of throwing it out
anyway. But so there's interesting questions about the use of this, diapers
maybe is even a better example, right? Because garbage you could make
a lot of arguments why that's not a problem in itself anyway.
But diapers, right, it's completely smelly and disgusting. How are you allowed
to go ahead and dispose of it on שבת? Shabbat. So this
is a principle of אגרף של רעי. agaraf shel rei. They let
you move it. So here too these ashes were completely... disgusting and
therefore they wanted to be removed. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, said
רבא, Rava, שתי תשובות בדבר, Shte teshuvos badavar, two responses to that
answer. חדא, Chada, number one, גרף של רעי מאיס והאי לא מאיס.
Grav Shel Re'i mois vehai lo mois. You know, right, so excrement
is disgusting. This is not disgusting. It's ashes, don't have use for
it, it's not like disgusting got to get rid of it. ועוד,
Ve-od, number two, גרף של רעי מיגלי, Grav Shel Re'i migli, the
feces of that, you know, that is exposed, the, you know, the
excrement.
האי לא מיכסי, Hai lo miksi, this, it's like a, you know,
one of those incense things that's got a lid on it, right,
and you put the incense in and maybe some fire, whatever. Anyway,
the whole thing of the ashes are closed, which raises a question
when you take the diaper and you make it into that tight
little pack and you put it in the plastic, maybe you're not
allowed to go ahead and take it out anymore. I don't know,
we're not going to talk about, not doing הלכה right now. Okay,
so anyway, but it does, it does raise that question about once
you've got the thing totally sealed, then you know maybe it loses
that status. Anyway, he says, so here anyway you have, you have
both of those things are not true, not just one of them
are not true like in the diaper case, both of them are
not true. It's not disgusting and it's sealed. So that can't explain
why he can move it. אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, so
rather רבא Rava said, כי הוינא בי רב נחמן, Ki havina bei
Rav Nachman, when I was in the house of רב נחמן, Rav
Nachman, הוינא מטלטלינן כנונא אגב קטמא, havina metalpelinan kanuna agav kitma, we
would move a, again, some type
of a, רש"י Rashi says, of a copper vessel that you would
use to burn coals in order to warm people up. You know,
you'd bring it front of them, a vessel that has burning coals.
And we would move that. We would move it what? אגב קטמא.
Agav kitma. Now that sounds like exactly the same. It sounds like
with its ashes. Okay, so how does, okay very nice, you just
repeated the point. You move something with ashes. But why does it
work? So רש"י Rashi says the whole difference here is in the
one word of אגב. Agav. That the first time it says we
moved the, we moved the גרף, Grav, we moved the incense burner
together with the ashes, so we can't understand it. The ashes were
a problem. Why isn't this a בסיס? basis רש"י Rashi says no,
no, no, I mean, the גמרא Gemara says or the way רש"י
Rashi explains what the גמרא Gemara, says is אגב קטמא. Agav kitma.
Actually, the ashes had a use and what allowed us to move
the vessel wasn't, it was the opposite, the ashes did have a
legitimate use and we were able to use the vessel because it
was a way of moving the ashes. What does that mean? What's
the ashes use? You know, because you can use the ashes to
let's say cover something up. You can use it as some type
of a, you know, for a function on שבת Shabbat. and יום
טוב. Yom Tov. So as long as there was ashes when שבת
Shabbat, began and as long as, you know, you're the type of
person that doesn't throw out these ashes because you're going to use
them for covering things, then the ashes aren't מוקצה. muktzeh, What do
you cover with them? I don't know. Let's say poop or something,
or some disgusting thing on the floor. Right, you spread ashes on
it. I didn't have nice, you know, stone floors or whatever. So
if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, אגב קטמיה, Agav kitmeih,
the keyword is אגב. Agav. That actually the ashes is what makes
it good, not creates the problem. So רש"י Rashi says it's about
10 lines before the lines get wide, רש"י Rashi says שהיו צריכים
לעפרה לכסות רוק או צואה, Shehayu tzerichim l'afrah lechasos rok o tzoah,
they would use the ashes to cover, you know, spit or excrement.
So, okay, so then the, so that's it. So therefore, I just
want to see one thing.
Does that change if you're rich or poor? I mean, you have
a nice marble floor, you'd be able to sweep it away.
Right, maybe if you don't have a use for it. But if
you do have a use for it, fine. Now,
the question of course is, you know, I don't get it then.
If the ashes had a use and the thing is just a,
is a pot or whatever it is or a, you know, of
an incense burner, who needs, you know,
what problem do you have? The ashes are fine and the vessel's
fine. What's the problem? רש"י Rashi says well maybe the problem is
that there's some still unburned wood chips in it and those only
have an איסור Issur use and those are real מוקצה. muktzeh. They
have no use on שבת. Shabbos. So now we've completely transformed the
case. It's not like the ashes were the problem and we had
to figure out why it's okay and what about בסיס basis and
maybe there was something else there that made it non-בסיס. basis No,
no, no. The ashes are good, vessels are good, all of those
are not מוקצה. muktzah The problem is what the גמרא Gemara doesn't
say, there's some wood chips there and those are מוקצה and then
it becomes allowed because it is a בסיס basis for the ashes
which now have become a דבר היתר Davar heter and for the
wood chips which are a דבר אסור. Davar assur. Okay, so that's
the גמרא's Gemara answer. Now,
the גמרא, Gemara now I do want to say one other thing
though about this בגדי עניים לעניים Bigdei aniyim l'aniyim because although the
גמרא Gemara used it in the context of a discussion
of is this thing מוקצה, it's got איסור Issur in it at
the time the גמרא Gemara was assuming ashes, but maybe it has
one thing that's also a support, which is this little piece of
incense, so that's what we discuss like the candlesticks and the napkin
on the tray and said no, no, no, if the other thing
is trivial it doesn't count. But it does raise interesting questions about
things that have different degrees of importance for different people. And I
just wanted to make a mention about this, I mentioned the other
day about a מוקצה question, came up yesterday as well. If I
made a vow and this fruit is, I can't eat this fruit,
but if you can eat the fruit, then maybe the fruit isn't
even מוקצה for me, because it's not like the fruit has no
purpose, I could feed it to you, right? So just because I
can't directly benefit from it doesn't mean that even for me it's
off limits. Okay, so interesting. Okay, so interesting question comes about when
there are different הלכה *halachic* practices. So there's a תשובה *Teshuvah* of
the רב פעלים *Rav Pe'alim* who was a rabbi in Baghdad in
the 19th century about can people who don't eat קטניות *kitniyos*, I
think he was talking about some Sephardim who have the חומרא *chumra*
not to eat קטניות *kitniyos*, can they cook קטניות *kitniyos* on פסח
*Pesach* for people who do? Is that an איסור *issur* of cooking
on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*? And number two is can
they move it? Is it מוקצה *muktzah*? Okay, and his basic answer
was was that yeah, it's not a problem, yes you can, it's
not a problem of מוקצה *muktzah*, because even if it's not fit
for you, it's fit for somebody else. But then he also got
into a discussion which others had preceded him with, about cigarettes on
יום טוב *Yom Tov*. And I mentioned this, right? If you feel
that it's if you believe it's אסור *assur* to smoke cigarettes altogether,
אסור *assur* to smoke cigarettes on יום טוב *Yom Tov* because it's
not a sort of צורך כל נפש *tzorech kol nefesh*, can you
move cigarettes? Or would you say that since there are other people
that פוסקין *pasken* it's מותר muttar, *muttar*, and for them obviously it's
not מוקצה *muktzah*, then it's not מוקצה *muktzah* for me either. And
he says, you know, in theory this could be different than the
קטניות *kitniyos* case. Because the קטניות *kitniyos* case everybody really agrees it's
מנהג *minhag*, it's חומרא *chumra*, I mean for Sephardim who eat קטניות
*kitniyos* it's certainly חומרא *chumra*, but anyway, even Ashkenazim it's מנהג *minhag*
etc. But here, you really think that the person who is smoking
is being עובר *over* on a is being מחלל יום טוב *mechallel
Yom Tov*, right? If you're if you're not a הלכה *halachic* pluralist,
so you think they're מחלל יום טוב *mechallel Yom Tov*. So you
really think for everybody this deserves to be מוקצה *muktzah*. He just
doesn't believe it. Okay, but I can't I can't help, you know,
the fact that he's misguided, but it really is מוקצה *muktzah* for
everybody. In the end, he sort of almost all the פוסקים *poskim*
say, even if you hold it's אסור *assur*, you know, enough of
a sort of of an אלו ואלו *eilu v'eilu*, because we're not
going to say that everybody who smokes on יום טוב *Yom Tov*
that we have all these, you know, is מחלל יום טוב *mechallel
Yom Tov*. It's interesting when we decide to say אלו ואלו *eilu
v'eilu* and when not. So we will acknowledge that יש להם על
מה שיסמוכו *yesh lahem al mah she-yismochu* and it's legitimate. And once
it's a legitimate הלכה *halachic* position, even if it's not your הלכה
*halachic* position, then it's not מוקצה *muktzah*, since it could be used
by someone else. So that does raise this is Jewish though, right?
Yeah, yeah, I mean let's say something not kosher.
Oh, yes, but so that's a discussion, but if you may, you
know, maybe you'll feed it to your dog or you'll have other
types of usages. But you have some use to it even if
that use is to give it to somebody else. Okay, so that's
an interesting question about unequal degrees of מוקצה *muktzah*, of things being
like off-limits. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
continues. Oh, I don't know, I guess I've been saying all along
it's רש"י Rashi, *Rashi*, it's the next five words in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. I don't know what's going with me. So let's take
a look about this wood chips. דהוה עבדינן בי רב נחמן הוי
מטלטלינן כנונא אגב קטמיה *Tee-avadin bay Rav Nachman havi mitaltelin kanuna agav
kitma*, I must be still asleep today. Okay, ואף על גב דאיכא
לשובי עצים *v'af al gav d'ika lashivay etzim*. So there it's explicit.
I'm sorry. So the wood chips are on it, so the ashes
are okay, the vessel's okay, because but the problem was was the
wood chips. So the whole חידוש chiddush *chiddush* was was that you
were allowed to carry it because you were allowed to move the
wood chips because everything else was okay and it was not a
בסיס basis *basis*. So let me just check רש"י Rashi *Rashi*. Hold
on.
Right. Okay, fine. Right, right, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* just adds, I was
confused because רש"י Rashi. *Rashi* is just adding the obvious point that
in the case of the of the incense burner, there was also
a case with the wood chips. So both of these are being
made into parallel cases. The ashes are okay, the vessel's okay, the
wood chips were the problem. That's now being applied from here back
to the case of the incense burner. Okay, and now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* goes on.
Okay, מתיבי Meitvei, *ameisaivei*, ask on this. ושוין שאם יש בה שברי
פתילה שאסור לטלטל *V'shavin she-im yesh ba shivray ptilah she-assur l'taltel*. That
if the if the lamp has in it a burnt-out wick, a
piece of a wick, you cannot move the lamp. Now why can't
you move it? What about this? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says this
is רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. Presumably let's
say it was a lamp that was burning from before that burnt
before שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, because otherwise, you know, it is a problem
according to according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. So it's an old
lamp, and it's got it's got this little burnt-out wick. So why
are you allowed to carry it? I'm sorry, why are you not
allowed to carry it? Right? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says שאסור
לטלטל *she-assur l'taltel*. So hold on one second.
Right, right, right, sorry, I'm sorry. So okay, so here's the way
it is. So רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* always has a problem with
an old lamp. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*'s problem with the old lamp
is that it's מוקצה מחמת מיאוס *muktzah machmas miyus*, it's disgusting. But
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* normally has no problem with an old lamp.
He doesn't even have a problem with a lamp that went out
on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*. Okay, but the one case it says that
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* would admit is a problem is if it's
got a little piece of wick in it. Okay, that is a
problem. Now why is that a problem? Why is that piece of
wick, why why is that מוקצה *muktzah*? Okay, so let's take a
look what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says. Why or why is that not like... hold on, I'm sorry
one second. So it says like this, one second.
Right. Why is that piece of wick at all
significant and why should it make the נר ner מוקצה? So the
גמרא Gemara says, so what's the answer? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר אביי בגלילא שנו. Amar Abaye b'galila shanu. We're talking about in
the Galilee. Now how does that help at all? So if you
take a look at
רש"י, Rashi right רש"י Rashi says בגלילא שנו, b'galila shanu. the last
narrow line of רש"י Rashi says שחשיבות להם שיבי פתילה, shechashivut lahem
shivei ptila, for them there, you know, for them like what do
you call
it, fabric was very dear, so even a little wick was significant.
שאין בגדים של פשתן מצויים להם, she'ein bgadim shel pishtan metzuyim lahem,
they don't have a lot of linen garments.
הלכך לא בטילי ונעשית נר בסיס להם. hilkach lo batili v'na'asit ner
basis lahem. So
the נר is בטל, batel, but it's a little funny according to
רש"י. Rashi Right, what's the הוה אמינא? hava amina? If I told
you about a remnant of a wick, you would say, okay, it's
completely insignificant, it's like a stick or a stone, and then it
would be more obvious that it should be a בסיס basis and
a מוקצה. So the גמרא Gemara, says, wait, I got a problem,
what about the wick? Oh, the wick is important. And somehow because
it's important that we thought before was unimportant, now it's important, makes
it מוקצה. What's going on here? So תוספות Tosafot, says the issue
is the opposite. The issue is if you look at תוספות, Tosafot
בגלילא שנו, b'galila shanu, he says, give you where he says his
answer, he says שהיה להם רוב שמן, shehaya lahem rov shemen, the
first wide line of תוספות Tosafot at the beginning, ולכך לא בטלי
שיבי פתילה אגב שמן. ul'chach lo batli shivei ptila agav shemen. So
he says, look, here's the point is, the question was like this,
it's very much for תוספות Tosafot it's much better because it's exactly
comparable to the whole ashes and the wood chips thing in this
case. You if you have an old lamp that you didn't use
when שבת Shabbat. began, what does it have in it? It's got
oil and a little piece of wick. So why should I not
be able to move it? Well, isn't the lamp a בסיס? בסיס
to the oil and the wick. Okay, but the oil is
actually the oil actually is a like is a דבר היתר, davar
heter, right? Why should that be a problem, right? Because I can
use oil on שבת. Shabbat. So what's the problem? Okay, so תוספות
Tosafot says, you understand the question? Why isn't what? No, you weren't
using it on שבת. Shabbat, You weren't using it on שבת, Shabbat.
okay?
So maybe the wick makes the oil that's... what?
I thought the wick makes the oil disgusting.
You make an oil that can only be used for...
maybe it designates it as like lighter fluid and so on. Okay,
you could say, but according to תוספות Tosafot that was the question
of the גמרא. Gemara Why is this a problem? You've got oil,
it's a בסיס for a דבר מותר davar muttar and a דבר
אסור. davar assur. The wick is a דבר אסור davar assur that
we always accepted, but the oil is a דבר מותר. davar muttar.
That's the גמרא's Gemara answer. What's question, what's the answer that we're
talking about בגלילא שנו? b'galila shanu, That in the Galilee they had
a lot, a lot of oil. And since they had so much
oil, they had more oil than they knew what to do with,
the oil was considered completely trivial and it was the wick that
was the most important thing. So therefore it was primarily a בסיס
to the wick and not a בסיס to the oil. Now that
seems hard to believe. I mean, even if oil is super cheap,
that it becomes trivial compared to the wick, okay? But again, this
is a central גמרא Gemara because this says that when it comes
to the idea of a בסיס, if you want to make it
considered an equal בסיס to the דבר מותר davar muttar and דבר
אסור, davar assur, they have to really be of equal weight, okay?
So the way תוספות Tosafot reads this גמרא Gemara it is much
better, we understand what the question is, and we and it's directly
comparable to the earlier issue, okay? So, by the way, if you
just want to see something a little interesting, if you have on
your side רבנו נסים גאון, Rabbeinu Nissim Gaon, a commentary here, about
ten lines down he says, אמר אביי Amar Abaye בגלילא שנו. b'galila
shanu? He says, נטרחו בזה השינוי ששינה אביי הרבה מן החכמים ולא
שמעתי מהם כלום ולא מצאתי בו לאחד מן הגאונים פירוש. netarchu b'zeh
hashinuy sheshina Abaye harbe min hachachamim v'lo shamati mehem klum v'lo matzati
vo l'echad min hageonim perush.
And everybody tried to explain this, nobody had what, why is Galilee
different? Nobody had a good explanation. All the גאונים Geonim tried. אבל
טרחתי על שינויה, aval tarachti al shinuyah, I worked very hard for
the answer, ומצאתי במסכת נזיר umatzati b'masechet nazir and then he quotes
what תוספות Tosafot... quoted about the whole issue of, you know, that
in the Galilee they had a lot of oil so the oil
wasn't significant. But it's quite interesting because we sometimes sort of, you
know, don't appreciate the effort it takes to come up with these
answers and how much ground they're treading, you know, through all of
ש"ס Shas to find the relevant material. So he says, nobody could
figure this out for, you know, all these generations, I found the...
because תוספות... Tosafot. why is this... okay, because they had a lot
of oil because this גמרא Gemara and so on. Anyway, he was
רבנו נסים גאון, Rabbeinu Nissim Gaon, he was גאונים, Geonim, he was
earlier than תוספות. Tosafot Yes.
I was going to ask if תוספות Tosafot had access to רבנו
נסים גאון. Rabbeinu Nissim Gaon.
I don't know. I don't know if we have any evidence of
that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, so again the
issue here was, how do we answer the whole issue with the
ashes and whatnot? The ashes weren't מוקצה, there was wood chips, and
therefore it was an equal בסיס and the חידוש chiddush was when
it's a בסיס equally to two things, it's okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says, well what about this case of the wick? That seems
to be an issue where it's an equal בסיס and it's no
good because it is an equal בסיס to the oil. Isn't the
oil not a problem? And the answer is, it's in the Galilee,
there was so much oil, the oil wasn't significant, and therefore it
was seen primarily as a בסיס to the wick.
Exactly, hard for us to believe but that's the גמרא, Gemara that's
what אביי's Abaye answer is. לוי בר שמואל אפיכינהו לרבי אבא לרבי
הונא בר חייא דהוו קיימי אפתחא דבי רב הונא. Levi bar Shmuel
apichinhu l'Rabbi Abba l'Rabbi Huna bar Chiya d'havu kaimei apitcha d'vei Rav
Huna. So they found so he found לוי בר שמואל, Levi bar
Shmuel, רבי אבא Rabbi Abba and רב הונא. Rav Huna. Bar Chiya
בר חייא Bar Chiya was standing at the door of רב הונא,
Rav Huna, no relation. אמר להו Amar lehu and he said to
them, מהו להחזיר מיטה של טרסין בשבת? Mahu lehachazir mittah shel tarsin
be-Shabbat? Can you put back together a bed of like these טרסין
tarsim of like
metalworkers or רש"י Rashi. on Shabbat? Apparently these would be people that
would go from town to town and they would have these collapsible
beds, you know, and you fold it out and again it's not
just a folding thing, you're actually, you know, putting things into holes
and you screw them together, one of those types of an assembly
self-assembly bed. Can you put them together on Shabbat? What's the story?
Sort of like a candelabra case, right? You had the מנורה של
חוליות? menorah shel chulyot? Yeah, exactly, it's going back to the מנורה
של חוליות. menorah shel chulyot.
For some reason it's just a complete shift from the מוקצה, not
clear what the transition was although as Michael correctly reminds us we
did in the earlier discussion mention something similar about a candelabra, so
maybe the גמרא Gemara is bringing this in in order to wrap
that discussion up. But it does not make clear reference to that.
Okay, so what's the story? Can you put together this self-assembly bed
on Shabbat?
So אמר לה, Amar leh, he said to them, שפיר דמי, shappir
dami, it's fine. אתו לקמיה דרב יהודה, Atu l'kamei d'Rav Yehuda, they
came to רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. אמר, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
said, "What? What'd he say to you? הא רב ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו,
Ha Rav u-Shmuel d'amri taveihu, רב ושמואל Rav u-Shmuel both say המחזיר
מיטה של טרסין בשבת amachzir mittah shel tarsin be-Shabbat חייב חטאת, chayav
chatat, that if you do it you've transgressed biblical Shabbat, you're חייב
חטאת." chayav chatat. It's a pretty radical, one person says it's totally
מותר, mutar the other person says you're חייב דאורייתא. chayav d'Oraisa. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, מתיבי, I'll ask you on this, המחזיר
קני מנורה בשבת חייב חטאת. amachzir k'nei menorah be-Shabbat chayav chatat.
So here again, without mentioning our earlier discussion but perhaps alluding to
it, it says if you put back
the arms, you know, you assemble the branches of a מנורה menorah
on Shabbat you're חייב חטאת. chayav chatat. That actually is considered—now what's
the מלאכה? melacha? Again רש"י Rashi says it's not בונה boneh because
אין בניין בכלים, ein binyan b'keilim, but it is מכה בפטיש, makeh
b'patish, which raises the question: what difference does it make if it's
בונה boneh or מכה בפטיש, makeh b'patish, either way it's אסור, but
okay, so that's what you're doing, you're making a vessel. So here
it says that if you do an arm of the candelabra you're
חייב חטאת. chayav chatat. כנס ידים לא יחזיר ואם החזיר פטור. Kanas
yadim lo yachazir v'im hechazir patur. Now if you have one of
those things which is used for
like a
paint roller, paint roller and
you have an—you can extend the arm by adding on other pieces
of the arm, okay, and so you add on another piece of
the arm, לא יחזיר ואם החזיר פטור, lo yachazir v'im hechazir patur,
don't put it in and if you do you're exempt. Does not
explain what the difference is. But רש"י Rashi says here, right, that
the reason you're exempt is שאין זה גמרו שצריך לחזור ולפרקו תמיד.
she-ein zeh gemaro she-tzarich lachzor u-le-farko tamid. And this is a very
important distinction, which is, here you are constantly adjusting how long do
you want it to be, where you want to paint, so it's
never finished in any one state. Other types of things you might
take them apart, you might take apart the bed, but then you
construct it and that's the state it's supposed to be in, that's
its finished state, okay? Whereas something that you're constantly adjusting does not
have one particular finished state. So you should not do it, but
if you do it you're exempt, okay, אבל אסור, aval assur, but
it's forbidden. So רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, קרן עגולה חייב,
keren agulah chayav, קרן פשוטה פטור. keren peshutah patur. So he says
that—רש"י Rashi says this is a type of a musical instrument. So
if it's a type of a circular one then you are חייב,
chayav, if it's a normal one you're exempt. What's the difference? So
רש"י Rashi says, let me just quote the line in רש"י. Rashi
So he says like this: קרן עגולה מעשה אומן וצריך לתקוע בנקבים
בחוזק. keren agulah maaseh uman v'tzarich l'itkoa bi-nekavim b'chozek. All these are
important principles because this comes up a lot about adjustable things on
Shabbat. He says the one that is prohibited that you're חייב chayav
is it's a מעשה אומן, maaseh uman, it requires an expert. And
number two, you have to do it בחוזק, b'chozek, like you gotta
bang in, you know, it might have inserted this thing into this
hole but you gotta bang it in with strength. And that makes
the problem, okay, and it's a מלאכה. melacha. וקרן פשוט מכניסו ברווח
ודרכן לפרקן תמיד. v'keren pashut machniso b'revach v'darkan le-farkam tamid. And the
difference is the one that's not a problem is you're constantly taking
it apart and also it does not stick in like in a
permanent way, it remains somewhat loose, okay? So anyway, here we've got
this issue that we see that it says that all of this
evidence that it's חייב חטאת. chayav chatat. רב ושמואל Rav u-Shmuel says
the bed is חייב חטאת. chayav chatat. All these other examples about
this about this type of a of a מנורה menorah and this
other thing that you're חייב חטאת, chayav chatat, this musical instrument, so
how could they say the bed isn't a problem? So the גמרא
says אינהו דאמרי כי האי תנא, inu d'amri ki hai tanna, they
say like the following תנא, tanna, דתניא, d'tanya, we've learned in a
ברייתא, baraita, מלבינות המיטה וכראות המיטה ולבכים של סקיבס. malbinot hamittah v'charaot
hamittah v'levachim shel sakivas.
So the different types of the—like the רש"י Rashi says like the
foot of the bed, the stuff that the legs would screw into,
and the legs of the bed, and these לבכים של סקיבס levachim
shel sakivas which רש"י Rashi says are that these actually would be
sort of like guides you would put on a bow for your
arrow, the thing you put like in the middle of the of
the bow for the arrow, a crossbow? סקיבס, sakivas, anyway, לא יחזיר,
lo yachazir, do not put them in their place on Shabbat, ואם
החזיר פטור אבל אסור. v'im hechazir patur aval assur. But if you
do then it is forbidden but you are you are exempt but
it is forbidden. ולא יתקע, V'lo yitka, and but do not actually
like bang it in, you know, a fit, a tight fit. ואם
תקע חייב חטאת. v'im taka chayav chatat. And if you do it
then you're חייב חטאת. chayav chatat. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer, אם היה רפה. im hayah rafeh. Shimon Gamliel
says, look, if it's loose,
not only is it פטור אבל אסור, patur aval assur, it's actually
permissible. So they must have felt that the bed base was actually
a case where it was loose, and therefore they were going like
ר' שמעון Reb Shimon that said it was allowed. Now תוספות Tosafot
says that you'd like we should understand that רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel
who said that the bed case was חייב חטאת chayav chatat is
not that they were talking about the same case of being loose.
For one person to say, תוספות Tosafot says it's unlikely, not that
it doesn't happen, that one person says something is totally מותר mutar.
and the other says חייב חטאת, chayav chatat, you're violating a דאורייתא.
d'oraita. So תוספות Tosafot, says the case that רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel
said חייב חטאת chayav chatat was a tight fitting one, the case
where they said it was permissible was a loose fitting one. Now
this then becomes and maybe some people would have a middle position
where it's loose it's פטור אבל אסור, patur aval assur, but רבן
שמעון גמליאל Rabban Shimon Gamliel says if it's loose it's מותר. Now
these issues I mentioned to you are very important about these types
of things on שבת. Shabbat. I'll just say without giving a פסק
הלכה psak halacha that things are clearly problematic if it's got some
of the qualities we've mentioned here. Number one, תקע, taka, like it's
some type of a thing that you have to like bang in
and it's a tight fit, okay, that's a problem. Another thing which
isn't mentioned right which isn't mentioned here but comes up whatever in
other cases is something for example you have to like screw in.
You know, it's got a screw component to it, even if you're
not, you know, one case you could like use a screw with
a screwdriver, but sometimes you have like a screw on the thing
you that goes in the hole, you know, and you screw it
together. The things that are like you do some type of a
thing like banging it, screwing it and it's tight, you know, and
you're making a vessel, those are really problematic. The things that are
the best are things that are loose fitting and that generally are
adjusted on a regular basis, okay? And that would be like for
us the great example would be I think the leaf in the
table. All right, that leaf in a table, it doesn't like become
a tight fit, you just pull the table apart, you could say
oh when I push it together it's tight, but yeah, but it's
not like stuck together and, you know, it's made for regular types
of adjusting. Those are the types of things that are okay, you
know, the question becomes about things that fall somewhere in the middle
of those two extremes. Yes?
Musical many musical instruments right would fit this category of not being
banged in and easily adjustable.
Like what are you talking about?
Like a clarinet.
What do you do?
You tune it by pulling out a little bit or putting.
Oh but that see that's like adjusting something
within a שבות shevut issue, but in terms of whether it's a
בונה boneh issue, you know, that's like adjusting something but you're not
taking two separate pieces and bringing them together.
Yeah you are, if you put a clarinet, it comes in about
five pieces.
Oh I see, so you're actually
assembling. Yeah, actual assembly. So okay, so that would be a problem.
So number one is there it's like done when it's made. It's
not like the table or the or the you know or the
wallpaper applier where it has different states. There it's done, right? There's
an undone and there's a done. It's like the bed. Although the
גמרא did say that according to some opinions even the bed is
okay if it's loose. But I imagine there it's also tight when
you actually assemble it, no? No? How could you assemble? You're playing
a clarinet and the pieces are loosely held together?
Yeah, you could easily change it.
They have grease usually around the cork.
Yeah, they put grease on to make it slippery.
But that's in order to adjust, not, but it's still held. All
right, so you're saying it's a loose type of an adjust. But
it's screwed, right? No. It's not screwed, it's just like put in
and it's a loose. Oh, interesting. Okay, that might be similar so
that might be similar to the bed case.
I'm not saying I want to play a clarinet.
I understand. That might be similar to the bed case which is
a done state but even in the done
state it's loose.
Okay, that's interesting. What?
It's musical. I know it's מוקצה but he's not asking about מוקצה.
He's asking about בונה. boneh.
Yes. And it goes out of tune. Any toys?
Like what type of toys?
Like Lego?
So yeah, I think that things like Mr. Potato, look, the problem
with things like Lego or whatnot is people that when they're done
with it they leave it that way. They've got their little creation
especially those Lego kits which are more like model kits. Things that
are regularly sort of taken out, put together and taken apart and
you don't leave it that way is not a problem especially if
they're made for that, right? But sometimes there are some of these
where it's actually made tightly, you know, and those are more things
to concern about. Mr. Potato Head is not an issue.
So when something is actually too tightly and it comes a little
bit loose and then screwing it in, it's just to get it
that much tighter, then that would be מכה בפטיש? maka b'patish?
That could be, yes, if you're really finishing it. Okay, so now
the גמרא wraps this up. So the גמרא says like this, בי
רב חמא הוי מיטה גלניסא. Be Rav Chama hava mita galnisa. So
they had this bed, this מיטה גלניסא. mita galnisa. So רש"י Rashi
says it's basically this same type of bed like we were talking
about before, a rolling bed maybe from the word גלגל? galgal? I
don't know. Anyway a rolling bed, they had some type of assembly
bed. הוי מהדרי לה ביום טוב, hava mahadri leh b'Yom Tov, he
would put it together on יום טוב. Okay, maybe they had to
move it out of the סוכה, sukkah, you know, and then they
moved it back in so they had to reassemble it. אמר להו
חד מרבנן amar lehu chad m'rabbanan so one of the rabbis says
to him, to רבא, Rava, מאי דעתך? mai da'atach? Why do you
think it's okay? בנין מן הצד binyan min hatzad because you think
it's like making something with a שינוי? shinui? Now why is it
a שינוי shinui if that's how it's made? So רש"י Rashi says
well maybe when he assembled it he assembled it loosely and normally
would assemble it, it would be a tighter screw, it would be
screwed together tighter. Okay, so is that why you think it's okay?
מיהא דאיסורא דאורייתא ליכא איסורא דרבנן מי איכא? Me-hei de-issura de-oraitta lei-ka,
issura de-rabbanan mi ika? It might be that it's not biblical but
it should at least be forbidden rabbinically. So אמר ליה, amar lei,
so he said to him, I'm sorry, מי איכא, mi ika,
אמר ליה amar lei said to him, אנא כרבן גמליאל סבירא לי
דאמר אם היה רפוי מותר. Ana ke-Rabban Gamliel svira li de-amar im
haya rafuy muttar. Now, אנא כרבן גמליאל, Ana ke-Rabban Gamliel, as long
as it's a loose fitting it's okay. And again the חידוש of
this is not only that it's we're not גוזר gozer that it'll
be a case of tight or whatever, but even in this case
where it's something that has a finished state. It's unassembled and it's
assembled as opposed to again like the leaf and the table where
or you know the wallpaper applier where it has different states. Even
though it has an unassembled and assembled state, if it's loose it's
okay. All right and that is these are as you can imagine
very important for practical issues of הלכה. With that we are done
with, not yet with the פרק, perek, that's coming up almost, but
with this major major you know pages of discussion of מוקצה, and
it does seem like that it was brought in to wrap up
the thing that was mentioned before about the מנורה. menorah. Let's look
at the last משנה. mishnah נותנין כלי תחת הנר לקבל
ניצוצות. Notnin kli tachat ha-ner le-kabbel nitzotzot. You can put a vessel
underneath the lamp to catch the sparks so it doesn't set your
house on fire, ולא יתן לתוכו מים מפני
שהוא מכבה, ve-lo yitten le-tocho mayim mipnei she-hu mechabbeh, but don't have
water in the vessel because that'll actually cause the sparks to immediately
extinguish. So the גמרא says, והכא מבטל כלי מהיכנו, ve-hacha mevattel kli
me-heichano, remember that? How can you catch the sparks? Then the vessel
will be unusable because it's a בסיס to the sparks or indirectly
removing the sparks, whatever the ash is, so you shouldn't be allowed
to move a vessel for that purpose. So אמר רב הונא בריה
דרב יהושע ניצוצות אין בהם ממש. Amar Rav Huna berei de-Rav Yehoshua
nitzotzot ein bahem mamash. Eh, yeah, when those burn out they're like
nothing, they're tiny little you know little black marks or whatever, they
don't count, and therefore you can move the vessel. It's not like
a thing
that's מוקצה.
Okay. ולא יתן... ve-lo yitten...
What? Oh it adds a flame? That's true. But the flame is
significant even if it doesn't have a physical ממש. mamash. ולא יתן
לתוכו מים מפני
שהוא מכבה, ve-lo yitten le-tocho mayim mipnei she-hu mechabbeh, don't put water
in it because, לימא תנן סתמא כרבי
יוסי? leima tnan stama ke-Rabbi Yossi? This sounds like רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi דאמר גרם כיבוי אסור, de-amar gram kibbuy assur, you cannot indirectly
cause כיבוי. kibbuy. What was the story? We'll see later on you
have a fire that's spreading. What do you do to put it
out? So the rabbis say here's what you do. You fill up
a vessel with water and you put them around the fire, so
when the fire comes and it shatters the vessel, it'll extinguish, the
water will go, so the fire will put itself out. רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi doesn't allow that. Even indirectly causing כיבוי kibbuy is forbidden,
even in a case of a fire. Okay, basically by the way
the ראשונים rishonim say that we put out fires because we consider
all fires
סכנת נפשות. sakanat nefashot. Anyway, but it's clearly an issue if some
people's house burned down on שבת Shabbat. because of the שבת Shabbat.
lamps and so on. Anyway, so the גמרא says like this, so
this sounds like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi who says that גרם כיבוי
gram kibbuy is a problem and this presumably this is the same.
So the גמרא says ומי תיסברא? ve-mi tisbra? Does that make sense?
אימא דאמרי רבי יוסי בשבת? eima de-amri Rabbi Yossi be-Shabbat? When does
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi have a problem putting the vessels with water
down? On שבת. Shabbat. דערב שבת מי אמר? de-erev Shabbat mi amar?
Since when would he ever problem this? You set up this whole
arrangement before שבת. Shabbat, Okay, now that's not so clear right? The
משנה mishna. when it speaks might have been talking on שבת, Shabbat.
but we're going to see in a minute that we have a
ברייתא braita that says that. וכי תימא הכא נמי בשבת, ve-chi teima
hacha nami be-Shabbat, maybe here too the only problem is on שבת.
Shabbat. והתניא, ve-hatanya, we have a ברייתא: braita: נותנין כלי תחת הנר
לקבל ניצוצות בשבת. notnin kli tachat ha-ner le-kabbel nitzotzot be-Shabbat. You can
catch the sparks on שבת. Shabbat? You put a vessel to catch
the sparks. ואין צריך לומר מערב שבת, ve-ein tzarich lomar me-erev Shabbat,
and you can certainly put the vessel there from before שבת. Shabbat
ולא יתן לתוכו מים מפני שהוא מכבה מערב שבת, ve-lo yitten le-tocho
mayim mipnei she-hu mechabbeh me-erev Shabbat, and
but you can't have water in the vessel because that causes extinguishing
even on ערב שבת. erev Shabbat. ואין צריך לומר שבת, ve-ein tzarich
lomar Shabbat, certainly not on שבת. So why can't you have water
in it? Even for רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, his whole problem is
on שבת. Here's a problem even on ערב שבת erev Shabbat you
can't have water in this vessel. What's the big deal? אלא אמר
רב אשי, Ella amar Rav Ashi, says רב אשי: אפילו תימא רבנן,
afillu teima rabbanan, for and forget רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, even the
rabbis would agree this is a problem. שאני הכא מפני שמקרב כיבויה.
shani hacha mipnei she-mekarev kibuya. Here it's different because you are literally
sort of making close its extinguishing. Now what does this mean? So
רש"י says what it means is that actually this is not גרם
כיבוי, gram kibbuy, this is actual כיבוי. kibbuy. You've got water, it
falls right in the water, it goes out, that's actual כיבוי. kibbuy.
תוספות, Tosafot it's not actual... I mean it is actual כיבוי kibbuy
when it goes out, but you're not doing it. You left it
there, you walk away. So what does רש"י mean? Just putting the
water there because it's going to happen, that act of putting the
water there is an act of כיבוי. kibbuy. Even if it's going
to happen, it's going to happen later. So תוספות Tosafot says doesn't
believe רש"י even meant it. And where תוספות Tosafot, explains the גמרא
and he tries to explain רש"י means to say is, we're not
afraid you are going to be גורם כיבויו, goreim kibuya, you will
be putting the dish there as a spark is falling down, or
a spark is falling down and you'll lift up the dish. So
you will actually be part of the extinguishing at the moment and
therefore that is the problem of having the thing with water and
once we're afraid about that, we're afraid even ערב שבת erev Shabbat
don't do it. One of these things with fire that we don't
like you to do ערב שבת erev Shabbat because it'll come to
doing something problematic on שבת, for again for תוספות, Tosafos not by
leaving it there, but by actually moving it. Yes.
So I've seen some people have a basin
of
foil
So you mean how can so how can we do this? How
can we do the basin? So תוספות Tosafos, says, I think one
minute
no, that's a good question.
I think you're not intending for it to go out right, right.
Oh, the basin of oil is not there to make it go
out?
Yeah, the basin of oil is to be...
Yeah, so if you look at תוספות, Tosafos, right, three lines from
the bottom of תוספות, Tosafos. one, two, three, five lines from the
lines that get wider of תוספות. Tosafos ומה שרגילין uma sheragilin says
תוספות Tosafos end of the line, לתת מים בזכוכית שקורין למפא latays
mayim bizchuchis shekorim lampa ונותן עליה שמן בערב שבת. venosan aleha shemen
berev shabbos. He talks about a floating wick. So you've got floating
oil floating on water. So when it gets to the water, it'll
go out. So why isn't that this problem? אין זה קרוי כיבוי
בידיו ein ze kari kiyuv kibuyav כיון שאינו מתכוין לכיבוי כלל keivan
sheino miskaven lekibuy klal אלא להגביה את השמן. ella lehagbiya es hashemen.
Why is the water there? To keep the oil high. It's not
that you have the water there so that when it burns out,
it'll get hit water and extinguish. The water's there to keep the
oil high. So therefore he says לא שייך למגזר מידי שמא יעשה
בשבת ושרי. lo shayach lemigezar midi shema yaaseh beShabbat ushari. So he
says that's allowed in terms of floating. I don't know if that's
your scenario.
It's not the same thing because if a spark falls into oil,
it goes out. So how can you have floating wicks? Right.
Spark falls into oil, it goes out.
Yes. But I don't use the oil to put out.
It's not the
no, that's what so that is the same as what תוספות Tosafos
says. תוספות Tosafos just saying is, as long as what's there is
not in order to enable it to go out, it's not a
problem. That's exactly what תוספות says. Let's just I just want to
get started. We only have like two minutes. I want to at
least start the next פרק. perek. Okay. So הדרן לך hadran lach
let's start the next משנה. mishna. Although we got into a whole
digression about מוקצה it was the focus of the last פרק perek
was about putting things on the flame before שבת. And now we
get to a very other important category which is putting them in
some type of a wrap that will retain their heat. Okay. So
let's take a look. במה טומנין ובמה אין טומנין. bameh tommnin uvameh
ein tommnin. Let's just read the משנה. What can you sort of
there's got to be a word rather than bury insulate something in?
Thank you. And what can you not on ערב שבת? erev Shabbat?
אין טומנין לא בגפת ולא בזבל ולא במלח ולא בסיד. ein tommnin
lo begefes velo bezevel velo bemelach velo besid. You cannot put it
in the רש"י says like like the grape sticks, the remnants of
the grapes or with excrement or salt
or the sticks, the branches or seed or plaster. ולא בחול velo
vechol or sand, בין לחים בין יבשים bein lachin bein yaveshin whether
wet or dry. All these things will give off heat and retain
the heat of the things in it.
Does it refer to the food?
No, to the material that you're insulating it in. ולא בתבן ולא
בזוגין ולא במוכין velo beteven velo bezogin velo bemuchin and not in
straw or a זג zag is like right, grape skins, right. And
מוכין muchin is like also like pieces of cloth or whatever filler
of pillows. ולא בעשבים velo beasavin and not in grasses, בזמן שהן
לחים bizman shehen lachin when they are moist, אבל טומנין בהן כשהן
יבשין aval tommnin bahen keshehen yaveshin but you can when they are
dry because presumably when they are dry, they do not give off
the same degree of heat. And the basic principle, and we will
continue with this tomorrow, is the following: they did not want you
even ערב שבת erev Shabbat to insulate in something that adds heat.
Why? Because the best thing to insulate in, especially if you imagine
wood-burning stoves, right, what would be the best thing to insulate in
that would add heat? What do you the hot ashes. Okay. And
if you insulate in hot ashes, you'll come to stir the ashes
on שבת. So because we didn't want you to insulate in hot
ashes, we said don't insulate even ערב שבת erev Shabbat in anything
that's like hot ashes that actually adds heat. Okay. And this is
going to be our focus of discussion and the real important issue
that comes up. How is that different than the issues of leaving
it on the flame before שבת? But this is what our פרק
perek is devoted to is insulating things before שבת in things that
add heat.
Okay.